Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
I bow in respect before Lady Sourire.
What is it, sir, that you have to carry personally?
His Majesty specially sends this to you, My Lady.
My Lady, have a look if you please.
The sole is made of a famous variety of Lantian jade,
which feels soft and keeps your feet warm.
The shoes were hollowed and filled with assorted spices.
His Majesty calls it "fragrant steps".
The tips of the shoes are adorned with Hepu pearls.
Although not as valuable as the eastern pearls,
they are perfectly sized and lustred.
The most notable part is the upper, which is made of
Shu Brocade [Sichuan's silk brocade] with gold engravings.
The Shu Brocade is a real rarity.
Especially a piece with gold engravings.
I heard that a piece takes ten weavers three months
to produce and is worth 20 gallons of gold.
It's even rare to see a piece of Shu Brocade,
let alone a pair of shoes made of it.
I am grateful to His Majesty.
But I'm wondering where the Shu Brocade came from.
I remember that it was offered as tribute in February
to the Express and the Empress Dowager.
The new offering should arrive next February, shouldn't they?
This is a special gift from His Majesty, My Lady.
The Textile Department of Shu produced a new design
and sent it all the way to here.
They only offered this one piece.
His Majesty ordered the Household Department
to work day and night making the shoes.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Speak of the devil.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
You should put on these shoes.
I want to see you wearing them.
How do they look?
They fit you perfectly. I remembered correctly.
Remembered what?
I remembered your size correctly when I made the order.
But I've never told Your Majesty the size
of my feet?
How could I know not that of someone I share the pillow with?
I specially ordered mandarin ducks
[symbolizing lifelong couples] to be embroidered on it.
Your Majesty...
Huan Huan, is there something I did that made you unhappy?
You always seem to have something on your mind
since we came back from the Summer Palace.
No, there's nothing like that.
It makes me a little worried that
Your Majesty is so good to me.
Don't worry. I'll keep my promises and protect you.
I understand, Si Lang.
But you used to be just as fond of Consort Fleur and Meizhuang.
I am afraid that your fondness is not love.
Fondness evinces love.
What if there is no love?
Si Lang, would you make an exception for me?
I will rejoice in any amount of love in your fondness.
You're being silly.
“When will we trim the candle wick at the westward window,
and talk about this moment of the rain in the Daba Mountains?”
While we are trimming the wick here,
we have a clear sky of stars rather than raindrops.
The nights are clear here in Beijing,
but Yunlin's letter said that it rained a lot in Sichuan.
Fortunately, his rainy nights in the Daba Mountains were as beautiful as in the poem.
It eased his tiredness along the journey.
Look at this.
They spurred the fastest horse to deliver it.
"They galloped through the dust for a consort's smile".
[from a poem about delivering lychees to Yang Guifei]
Unfortunately, I'm not fond of this color.
You are what you wear.
It must be ablaze with colorful flowers.
Your Highness usually wears vibrant colors.
However, these colors are also elegant.
Since they don't usually produce Shu Brocade
[Sichuan's silk brocade] at this time of the year,
They must have acquired these two pieces with great effort.
They put a lot of thought into this gift indeed.
If Your Highness didn't notice,
These flowers were embroidered using moon-white threads intertwined with silver threads.
It will shine brightly in the sun.
That must be so difficult for them.
But everyone should know that I get what I want
whether it is rare or costly.
Yes.
Unlike someone wearing the Shu Brocade shoes but
"still not a princess in a royal garment".
I shall have the brocade made into two dresses.
Everything seems fine ...
except that I don't recognize what flower this is.
Yes, Your Highness usually received patterns of peony or phoenix.
This is quite special.
Does anyone know what flower this is?
My Lady, this is the morning glory,
also known as "the face of eventide" .
How rustic!
This flower blooms at dawn and withers the nest morning.
It fades before even seeing the sunlight.
Stop!
You are not allowed to utter such inauspicious words.
Idiots!
The Textile Department of Shu must have lost their minds.
How dare they offer me brocade with these ill-fated flowers?
- Song Zhi.
- Yes.
Tear them up and send them back to the Textile Department.
Yes.
Your Highness, they probably didn't know about this uncommon flower.
Although the brocade itself is insignificant, destroying it can churn up gossip in the palace.
Since most people don't know this flower,
Your Highness might as well award the brocade to an unaware mind.
I'll give it to her.
Who?
She already has the matching shoes .
A complete outfit will accentuate her place in His Majesty's heart.
Sourire, you are finally back.
You all went to the Summer Palace.
I was left alone all this time.
It was so boring.
Wasn't your etiquette instructor with you?
She was always critical of me being too talkative.
She told me to cultivate inner peace.
"You would be favored by His Majesty
if you are more like Attendant An".
You should listen to her. She is your instructor.
She also said that
I didn't even have a chance to talk to His Majesty
after an entire year living in the palace
and that I'm noisy all day.
I will have to obey even more rules if I see His Majesty.
I'd rather not.
Tell that to His Majesty when you see him.
My Lady, Mr Zhou from the Palace of Earthly Honor.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
Rise.
Thank you, Lady Sourire.
Her Highness Consort Fleur just received two pieces of Shu Brocade.
Her Highness found the colors clean and refreshing,
so she had them made into two garments for you.
I thank Her Highness.
JinXi, take them.
To Her Highness,
the dresses are elegantly colored and exquisitely crafted.
However, the priest from the Baohua Hall said
Lady Sourire clashes with "shu" [zodiac animal rat] this year
which is a homophone of the "Shu" Brocade.
It would be okay to step on the Shu Brocade as a pair of shoes.
But if the Shu Brocade are made into dresses ...
I'm afraid you will have to wear them next year, My Lady.
Jinxi, if I'm understanding correctly,
Lady Sourire cannot wear the dresses if they are awarded by Her Highness?
Indeed, Lady Sourire is the now in high favor.
She would not even look at gifts from anyone else.
Her Highness always says that
an upstanding person should have no fear of the evil spirits.
Although we cannot distrust the priests,
Her Highness's grace and blessings
will also protect you from evil, My Lady.
Jinxi was reminding me with good intention.
You must not misunderstand her, sir.
Please inform Her Highness that I will thank her personally another day.
If so, I shall take my leave.
Come here. Let me look at it.
The dress is so beautiful!
Sourire, why do you look unhappy after receiving such beautiful dresses?
What kind of flower is this?
I have never seen it before.
This is "the face of eventide", the morning glory.
The morning glory? Does it symbolize something?
The flower is beautiful indeed.
But this is such a sudden gift.
I don't quite understand.
Nor do I.
It's an odd and unexpected surprise.
Sourire, isn't the dress a perfect match
for your Shu Brocade shoes?
You should wear it on the Chrysanthemum Day in October.
You will put all the other concubines to shade.
Put them away for now.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesty.
You may rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Have a seat.
Good that you got a chance to visit me today.
It is my duty to serve Your Majesty.
While His Majesty is busy with the state affairs,
I must fulfill filial piety on his behalf.
That is very sweet of you.
The nights are getting cold in autumn.
I hope Your Majesty's cough has improved.
It has.
I remember Your Majesty is sensitive to cold.
I ordered a fox fur cloak for Your Majesty.
Is this the fur of black foxes?
Yes, Your Majesty.
My brother quelled rebellions in Qinghai.
He hunted two black foxes by chance.
I thought only Your Majesty could bring out the magnificence of this color.
So I had the fur made into this cloak for Your Majesty.
I know Your Majesty is a devout believer of Buddha.
The lining is specially embroidered with the lotus pattern in Tibetan Buddhism.
I hope Your Majesty would like my humble gift.
I appreciate your kind thought.
Bamboo, take it.
Yes.
Why do you dress so plainly today?
Although Your Majesty may see me as an unseasoned concubine,
I am not young compared to the new concubines.
I should dress with more modesty.
Noble Lady Sourire and Attendant An would dress more nicely.
I do hear about Noble Lady Sourire a lot.
I only remember she looks lovely.
What a shame that Your Majesty hasn't seen her recently.
His Majesty awarded her a pair of
Shu Brocade shoes woven with gold.
Even the sole is made of jadeite.
Noble Lady Sourire also made two dresses from Shu Brocade.
What an outfit of glamor!
Is that so?
But I remember the Shu Brocade is not produced at this time of the year.
Lady Sourire is sweet and endearing.
How could His Majesty say no to her requests?
I'm really curious how costly her complete outfit is.
She is new to the palace.
The Emperor regards her as a child.
That's why she receives more care from him.
You have been favored by him for years
and understand the standards of decorum.
You should remind him.
Yes, Your Majesty.
In my view, you take priority in his heart.
He personally chose the ingredients of Pleasancy
and had it concocted for you.
Of the entire palace, who else has he been so thoughtful to?
Come here.
(gasp) I'm unworthy of Your Majesty's gift.
It's okay.
This hair dangler was awarded by the former Empress
when I was promoted to Consort.
You are as pretty as a flower in your prime age,
and ranked highly among the concubines.
You should dress accordingly.
I think this hair dangler is perfect for you.
I thank Your Majesty.
I care for you the same way I care for the emperor.
Go change to a brightly-colored dress.
He will like it.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Your Highness's hair dangler is so pretty.
But it pains me that we didn’t take out our anger on Zhen Huan.
I don't need you to remind me.
But it was unusual that Her Majesty was so nice to me.
Exactly.
Light the sandalwood.
And bring my Lotus Sutra.
Your Majesty also wishes to dissipate
the sourness of jealousy in the chamber.
Jealousy is a common brew in the harem.
I've been accustomed to its smell.
So have I, Your Majesty.
But Consort Fleur made such a fuss about it.
It is hard to imagine what Lady Sourire is like!
You know Consort Fleur. She is the jealous type ...
ever since she married in.
The emperor is to blame for this.
He's still being inconsiderate at this age.
I still have to worry about him.
Your Majesty must not worry.
Your Majesty is the last person who should worry.
Go to the Hall of Mental Cultivation
and tell him to come over after work.
Yes, Your Majesty.
His Majesty the Emperor!
Peace and grace to Mother.
Have a seat.
It’s getting colder these days.
Why didn't you put on a coat?
I'm not cold. I just came from the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Su Peisheng, you should have reminded him.
It was my negligence.
I beg for Your Majesty's forgiveness.
Su Peisheng is a very considerate person.
But even so, he couldn't attend to everything.
If Mother say so, I will put on a coat after I go back.
All right. Su Peisheng, you may rise.
I thank for Your Majesty.
I will be most attentive to serve His Majesty in the future.
Speaking of service,
not only should the servants be careful,
but the concubines should also pay more attention.
Is the Noble Lady Sourire conscientious ?
That is hard to say.
If I say she is,
Mother would blame her for not reminding me to dress warmly today
and me for being partial to her.
If I say she is not, she is a truly thoughtful person.
But I have been busy with work and
haven't seen her for three or four days.
Your Majesty said you are not partial to her.
But that is veritable partiality.
Madam, please don't tease me.
When you were occupied with the state affairs,
you did not see her for merely three or four days.
So how often do you see Consort Fleur,
the Empress,
and Concubine Estime and the other concubines?
It's all right to pay fewer visits to the harem when you are busy.
But it will upset some concubines if you manifest partiality for the others.
You are right, Mother.
I will remember your advice.
The black fox fur of such quality ...
must be produced in Qinghai.
Your Majesty has sharp eyes and a sharp mind.
You can see the black fox fur in such a dim chamber.
I hope you will also see the harem and the court
"as bright as a blazing fire."
This fur cloak is made of the black fox fur indeed.
Consort Fleur specially had the lining embroidered
with the lotus pattern in Tibetan Buddhism.
The inside and the outside are mutually reinforcing.
I completely understand, Mother.
I heard that you awarded Consort Fleur a hairpin today.
I believe it will be beautifully lit by the candlelight at night.
I am going to admire its lustre.
favor and force is not only applicable to the imperial court
but also the harem.
While the rebellions in the northwest are settling down,
the tribal chiefs in the southwest remain an internal threat.
It will require great effort to pacify them.
Nian Gengyao is capable and loyal.
You should assign important duties to him
as long as he does not become imperious.
It is an extraordinary feat to pacify the west.
Nian Gengyao will pay respect to the palace in October.
I will highly reward him for sure.
Consort Fleur is running out Pleasancy.
The making of this incense is a complicated process.
Do you wish to stop awarding it to her?
Since she is very used to using it,
I shall not stop giving it to her.
Your Highness.
Is my brother back?
Yes, the great general has returned to the court from the west
and he went to pay respect to His Majesty.
His Majesty has always been generous to the great general.
They must be having an important conversation right now.
Of course.
But it's already lunch time.
They need to have lunch even though they have important matters to discuss.
Your Highness.
His Majesty invites Your Highness to have lunch
in the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Please wait outside.
I will go immediately.
Although there are a variety of dishes in the palace,
I’m not sure what you like to eat.
You can try any dish as you wish.
If they really don't cater to your taste,
I’ll order some dishes for you from Consort Fleur’s kitchen.
I do not deserve Your Majesty saying so.
It is an ultimate grace to be allowed to have a meal with Your Majesty and Her Highness.
Please sit.
We are having lunch as a family.
Let's not spoil the meal by standing up for thank yous and sorries.
Sit.
I thank Your Majesty and Your Highness.
This grilled lamb is fresh and tender.
It's one of my favorite dishes. You should have some.
This is delicious. I thank Your Majesty.
Gengyao, you must be served by the servants
when His Majesty awards you a dish.
I apologize for my discourtesy before Your Majesty.
Having gone through a succession of wars,
you must be accustomed to personally attending to everything.
It’s all right.
I should obey the rules in the palace.
No, just act as you will.
Rules are the courtesy between monarch and subjects,
not the inhibition among family members.
Yes.
The cubilose duck in front of me looks good.
May I trouble Mr Su?
Great General, please.
You vanquished Lobsang Tendzin in just fifteen days
and gradually cleaned up the remnant troops in the past eight months.
You pacified the northwest and inspired awe in the western territories.
You’re a true benefactor to me.
I’m humbly undeserving of Your Majesty’s compliment.
Since I acceded to the throne not very long ago,
stability has not been fully established in and out if the court.
While the lords are eagerly ready for a revolt,
a rebelling frontier will overwhelmingly put me
between the hammer and the anvil.
Your extraordinary feat not only deserves my awards
but also everlasting gratitude from me,
my descendants, and all the citizens.
None of my descendants will be allowed to be unfaithful.
None of my citizens will be allowed to be disloyal.
While Her Highness Consort Fleur
dedicates herself to the harem,
I am faithfully serving Your Majesty on the borders.
We humbly exert our utmost effort to serve Your Majesty.
Consort Fleur has been my caring and considerate
housekeeper all these years.
And you’ve been my right-hand man on the battlefields.
I'm fortunate to have you as the champion of the borderlands.
If there were ten more officials like you,
I wouldn't not have to worry about governance anymore.
I thank Your Majesty.
Here is to you both.
Yes.
Has it been peaceful in Yun-Gui and Shaan-Gan?
Everything is good.
However, before I came back to Beijing,
I heard that the Xieersu tribe near
Mount Zhuozi had been rebellious.
I was afraid they might riot.
As I expected, the news arrived yesterday that they
created a disturbance in Zhuanglang, Gansu Province.
I believe it won't take long to quell the mob.
Certainly, Your Majesty.
However, I heard Xieersu had been conspiring with Xinjiang's Geerdan to form a restraining force on our troops.
We must be cautious about that.
What’s your opinion on that?
Xieersu is just a small tribe.
Sending over a high official would seem like
we are paying excessive attention.
Yet an indifferent attitude would escalate this internal hazard.
Hence I would make a bold suggestion to send
my second son Nian Fu to quell the unrest.
He is quite experienced despite his age.
I would like to let him have an opportunity like this.
Your Majesty, I can’t interfere in governance.
I should avoid listening to this conversation between Your Majesty and my brother.
This is both state affairs and family matters.
It's all right if you stay.
Consort Fleur is right.
It an exceptional honor to dine with Your Majesty.
I shouldn't have been talking about work at a family reunion.
Very well then.
Let's keep eating.
The weather is getting cold.
We will start to have a hot pot for every meal from the 15th of October.
Although it's the 14th today, His Majesty ordered the
Imperial Kitchen to prepare the assorted hot pot for you.
You must be grateful to His Majesty's thought in your meal.
I thank Your Majesty for the heavenly grace.
Sharing the same hot pot will keep you warm
while having the same mind makes me even warmer.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Help yourself.
Yes.
I bid Your Highness goodbye.
I bid Great General Nian goodbye.
Oh my, Gengyao,
I was having the meal with my heart in my mouth.
What’s going on with you?
When His Majesty said he the grilled lamb was his favorite.
How could you eat it before His Majesty lifted his chopsticks?
More than that, how could you ask Su Peisheng to serve it to you?
Do you not know who Su Peisheng is?
He is the direct servant of His Majesty for decades
ever since His Majesty was young.
How could you order him around?
You know me.
I hate the foul stench of eunuchs.
If I had to obey the rules of the palace,
I should want the "head and face" of the eunuchs.
If i may say so,
does the wars won on my horseback
not deserve the service of a eunuch?
He is the servant of His Majesty and me.
It's all right that he serves you one single time.
But don't do that again.
Li Bai, with his stinky poems, could even have Gao Lishi
[the highest eunuch at that time] to remove the his boots for him.
It was Su Peisheng's honor to serve for me.
Other than that, there are things that His Majesty can say but you can't.
Mm?
His Majesty was being polite when he said we are a family.
But your saying that oversteps the bounds of propriety.
Why were you drunk before you drank?
Shilan, it seems that living in the palace narrowed your mind.
I was just echoing His Majesty's words.
And in fact, His Majesty is our family.
You are his beloved consort and I am his brother-in-law.
Are we not kin to him?
Thanks to Buddha, His Majesty didn't blame you.
His Majesty even let you walk me back to my palace.
I reckon he's not angry.
What's wrong with you?
Is it the Empress who's been giving you trouble?
She's not capable of that.
It's the new concubine Lady Sourire.
She always fawns over His Majesty
and turned His Majesty against me.
It was because of her that His Majesty suspended
my authority in palace management to this day.
How dare a Noble Lady offend you as her superior?
She is in high favor.
What can I do?
I heard that her father is a deputy minister.
Oh? What's his name?
Zhen Yuandao.
Very well.
Since his daughter is giving you trouble,
I will get him in trouble!
I am fortunate to have your support.
Otherwise, how much more miserable my life would be!
Don't worry, I got you back.
Your Majesty, General Nian is back.
Your Majesty.
Have a seat.
I'm honored to obey.
General Nian, please have a cup of tea.
I denounced to Your Majesty Zhao Zhiyuan,
the Governor of Zhi Li.
He should not occupy this position for his foppery and mediocracy.
I wonder if Your Majesty has adjudicated.
If you think he is unqualified, I will dismiss him.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Although we are monarch and subject in public,
we are family at home.
I must be an excellent emperor to honor your hard work.
Yes.
And you must be an outstanding general to reciprocate my appreciation.
We must leave a good name through generations.
I will not hesitate to sacrifice my life
in reciprocation for Your Majesty's grace.
Just sit there and make yourself comfortable.
I am tired of your frequently standing up to thank me.
Yes, Your Majesty.
For your commitment and contribution, I reward you
a two-ocellus peacock feather [a symbol of distinction on hat],
a patching dress with four dragon medallions,
a yellow belt, a purple halter and lead, and 1000 taels of gold.
You've had a long day.
You should go back for a good rest.
Get back to me another day.
I humbly thank Your Majesty.
Xiao-Xiazi heard it clearly ...
that His Majesty called General Nian his "benefactor ".
Your Majesty.
Autumn, why it is getting cold all of a sudden?
Because of the wind from the northwest.
Shall I bring Your Majesty a coat?
A coat will not change the weather.
His Majesty has only been visiting Consort Fleur.
He didn’t even step into the Palace of Great Benevolence.
The Palace of Great Benevolence had always been cold.
It warmed up once in a while when His Majesty visited.
But now, it truly has turned cold.
I wonder how warm the Palace of Great Benevolence would be ...
if His Majesty gave it as a gift to his "benefactor".
Your Majesty has only been staying with me lately.
You should visit the other concubines as well.
If you say so, I’ll go visit Consort Astuce.
Your Majesty!
You know I didn't mean it.
It’s late now.
Your Majesty should stay.
I knew you wouldn't let me.
I remember I always stayed with you when we were newly married.
Sometimes I would have neglected Yixiu [the empress],
even when she had just become my primary wife.
Before I married into the family, Your Majesty
had a lot of nights staying with Her Majesty.
Her Majesty married into the family earlier than me.
Your Majesty will make it fair by spending more time with me.
I wish I could.
But as the emperor,
I have to manage the state affairs
and a harem with more concubines.
I can’t neglect them all just for you.
If Your Majesty says so, Your Majesty must be
thinking of someone else when you're with me.
Don’t be temperamental.
You were a Lord Consort [secondary wife of a lord]
and now a Consort.
I need you to dedicate your mind to the
people and things in the palace for me.
Okay?
The empress is in ill health.
You must carry some of the burden for her.
Yes, I understand.
Sourire, you are really keen on concocting the Harmony Perfume.
You've been working on it for more than a week.
How come you are not tired of it?
I need to do something to pass the long and lonely nights.
Hasn’t His Majesty visited you?
Not since he was here for lunch six days ago.
You remember the days so well.
I can't even recall when was the last time.
It's probably been more than half a month.
But I can't complain.
Consort Astuce said she had not seen His Majesty
since she came back to the palace.
The cold autumn killed all the flowers
except for Consort Fleur.
While she can take the pleasure seeing all the
"bare branches", we mind for ourselves.
Are you not feeling well?
I caught a cold this morning.
I will be fine after a day or two.
Don't worry.
Actually, the recipe for the Harmony Perfume is lost.
It is rarely seen even in the palace.
There's no fun if everything is cut and dried.
Experimenting with the spices is an enjoyable pastime.
It would be great to use the
Harmony Perfume in winter if we are successful.
It would bring you to a sea of flowers
when roasted by the stove heater.
Exactly. My father used to own a spice business
for over 10 years before he had a public office.
He got lots of secret recipes for incense by luck.
I studied them for a few days
and found several ingredients that might be useful.
That's great! I will write them down.
Your Majesty always likes to hear Attendant An singing.
It's been a while.
How about we have her over to sing for Your Majesty?
It would be a great pleasure for me as well.
It's late already. It would bring her trouble.
Your Majesty ...
It's all right if you like.
Zhou Ninghai.
Yes, Your Highness.
Request her to come.
Yes.
Sourire, I can read your mind from your writing.
What's wrong?
In your erudite mind, is the 藿 character written this way?
Where is the 艹 radical on top?
Did it fly with your heart to His Majesty?
Watch your sassy tongue.
I hope a behest from His Majesty would
take you away now and quiet you down.
I wasn't being sassy.
You were just self-conscious.
Look for yourself. Here!
I bow in respect before Lady Sourire and Attendant An.
Peace to you, My Ladies.
What brought you here, Mr Zhou?
His Majesty would like to hear Attendant An singing,
and requested her presence at the Palace of Earthly Honor.
His Majesty is with Consort Fleur now.
It's inappropriate for me to intrude.
What about I sing for His Majesty tomorrow?
His Majesty is waiting.
My Lady, you would have to personally
defy His Majesty's order.
I cannot say it for you as a servant.
Jinxi, bring my zither.
My Lady ...
I'll go with Attendant An and accompany her singing
with zither to entertain His Majesty.
I hope Her Highness won't mind me joining them.
My Lady, if you are willing to perform,
Her Highness will surely be pleased to see you both.
Please follow me.
May peace be with Your Majesty.
Peace to Your Highness.
- All rise.
- I thank Your Majesty.
Lady Sourire ...
why did you come along so late on a cold night?
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.